René Char Papers, 1929-2007 (bulk 1939-1980): Finding Aid C1599
Manuscripts Division
René Char Papers
1939-1980
1928-2019
Manuscripts Division
Char, Marie-Claude.
Char, René (1907-1988)
C1599
64 boxes
58 linear feet
Consists primarily of the correspondence of 20th-century French poet René Char (1907-1988); a smaller subset includes correspondence and records documenting his involvement with the French Resistance during World War II.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
For preservation reasons, original analog and digital media may not be read or played back in the reading room. Users may visually inspect physical media but may not remove it from its enclosure. All analog audiovisual media must be digitized to preservation-quality standards prior to use. Audiovisual digitization requests are processed by an approved third-party vendor. Please note, the transfer time required can be as little as several weeks to as long as several months and there may be financial costs associated with the process. Requests should be directed through the Ask Us Form.
Appraisal
No materials were removed from the collection during 2018 and 2022 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Arrangement
The order of the materials, most likely established by René Char and Marie-Claude Char, was mostly maintained.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Marie-Claude Char in 2018 (AM 2018-88); and in 2019 (AM 2020-38).
Librairie Benoît Forgeot brokered both purchases.
Scope and Contents
Consists primarily of the correspondence of 20th-century French poet René Char (1907-1988), including correspondence and records documenting his involvement with the French Resistance during World War II.
Most of the description included here is from an inventory provided by Marie-Claude Char and Librairie Benoît Forgeot, which brokered the acquisition of the collection.
Char, Marie-Claude.
Biographical / Historical
Marie-Claude Char is a French editor and publisher. The widow of poet René Char, she has been involved in disseminating her late-husband's work, and preserving the history of his role in the French Resistance.
Char
Biographical / Historical
Celebrated 20th-century French poet René Char (1907-1988) published more than 30 volumes of poetry, criticism, and plays during his lifetime, many of which were widely translated. He frequently collaborated with both writers and artists, including Georges Braque, Joan Miró, and Nicolas de Staël. He was also decorated military veteran, receiving recognition for his service in the French army and his involvement with the French Resistance during World War II.
In the early 1930s, Char was active in the surrealist movement, joining a community of writers and artists that included Louis Aragon, André Breton, and Pablo Picasso. From 1939 to 1940, he served as a private with the 173e RA (Régiment d'Artillerie) in Alsace for which he was awarded the Croix de Guerre. During the Nazi Occupation, Char and his first wife Georgette, who were under surveillance, took refuge in the town of Céreste. It was there, in 1941, when Char began his involvement with the Resistance. By 1943, under the nom de guerre Captain Richard Alexandre, he became the commander of landing operations and parachute drops in the Basses-Alpes (Alpes-de-Haute-Provence) as head of Section Atterrissage Parachutage (SAP) Region 2. Char was awarded the Medal of the Resistance and also named to the Legion of Honor for his service. His prose poem collection Feuillets d'Hypnos documents his wartime experiences.
After the war, Char moved to the Luberon Mountains of southern France, near his birthplace. In his later years, he was involved with anti-nuclear activism.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground movements -- France. -- Sources; World War, 1939-1945 -- Poetry. -- Sources; Poets, French. -- 20th century -- Sources; France -- History -- German occupation, 1940-1945. -- Sources; Correspondence
- Papers on the French Resistance, 1939-1980; 1929-2007; 11 boxes
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  AM 2018-88
  Scope and Contents
  Materials consist primarily of correspondence and official records that document 20th-century French poet René Char's activities during World War II, in particular, his involvement with the French Resistance as head of Section Atterrissage Parachutage (SAP) Region 2 in the Basses-Alpes.
  Most of the correspondence includes incoming letters from fellow Resistance fighters that date from during and after the war. Records primarily include those relating to SAP, such as memos, official documents, reports, and personnel files (fiches individuelles or fiche de renseignements) that provide biographical information and information about individuals' service. Also included are some photographs as well as a few manuscripts and related materials, in particular, drafts of addresses by Char and others, and correspondence relating to Char's book of poetry, Seuls demeurent. While most materials are to or about Char, there are several dozen letters, documents, and writings from and by Char scattered throughout the collection. Some materials in the collection also relate to Char's widow, Marie-Claude Char, specifically her involvement in events and projects relating to her husband and his papers.
  Note that names and materials of a similar nature are represented throughout the collection.
  - Resistance I, 1941-2004; 2 boxes
    Primarily includes letters from fellow réfractaires. A few documents as well as a couple of manuscripts of speeches by Char are also included.
    - Madeleine Baudoin, with a Draft Response by Tina Jolas, 1972 December- 1973 January; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 1)
      Envelope includes autographed note from Char, "a renvoyer aux oseilles!"
    - Vercors and Jeanne Bruller, 1947-1950; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 2)
      2 letters.
    - Georges Lambrichs, 1947 January 8; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 3)
    - Letter from Amis des Éditions de Minuit, 1947 December 15; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Alain Krivine's Father, 1944 October 17; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 5)
    - André Rousseaux, 1950-1970; 1 box
      67 letters and postcards, primarily, from André Rousseaux and his family.
      - André Rousseaux, 1950-1959; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 6)
      - André Rousseaux, 1960-1970; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 7)
      - Autograph Letter from Char to Rousseaux, 1950 August 17; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 8)
      - Note from Char Giving News of His Mother, 1950 December 8; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 9)
      - René Char Letter to a Friend [Rousseau?], 1951 August 28; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 10)
    - Letter Addressed to Captain Alexandre from One of His Subordinates, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 11)
    - Collective Letter to Char, 1978 November; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 12)
      Written on the back of the menu of the traditional meal of the Résistants du Vaucluse.
    - René Armand, 1944 November 12; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 13)
    - Letters from SAP Members, 1944-2004; 1 box
      - List of Names Represented, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 14)
      - JRivière alias Charles Henri, 1947 February 1; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 15)
      - A. Dumay, 1947-1948; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 16)
        4 letters and 1 telegram from A. Dumay.
      - Bellion, 1957 March; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 17)
      - Azan, Général A., 1945 March 5; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 18)
      - Broïda, E., 1945-1948; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 19)
        7 letters.
      - Bouvier, Emile, 1952 June 20; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 20)
      - Clément, 1945 February 2; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 21)
        Aspiring SAP
      - Fradisse, Olga, 1944 February 11; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 22)
      - Gairaud, Jean, 1948 March 13; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 23)
      - Garcin, Jean, 1979 February 9; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 24)
        Typed letter from Char to Jean Garcin.
      - Gay, Jeanette, 1945 March 13; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 25)
      - Imbert, Achille, 1954 October 19; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 26)
      - Martin, Paul, 1944-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 27)
      - Martin, A., 1946 July 17; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 28)
      - Martin, Jean, de Reillanne, 1947; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 29)
      - Navi, Ferdinand, 1947 January 15; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 30)
      - Masoiro, Joseph, 1945 February 27; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 31)
      - Micheli, 1945 May 23; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 32)
      - Mourier, Captain, 1945-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 33)
      - Nicault, Claude, 1945 February 14; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 34)
      - Panza, A., 1945-2004; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 35)
        Includes certificate of the Mayor of Vaucluse and 1 letter to Marie-Claude Char from 2004.
      - Pelloux, Sabine et Lucien, 1946-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 36)
        3 letters.
      - Plagne (Chef d'escadron), 1945 March- June; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 37)
      - Poix, 1945 May- June; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 38)
      - Rua, Jean, 1946 May 12; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 39)
      - Roux, Emile, 1951 October 2; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 40)
      - Seignon, Marceau, 1945-1977; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 41)
        5 letters.
      - Thro, Henri, 1945 January 30; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 42)
      - Villa, 1951; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 43)
      - Walquemanne, 1945 May- December; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 44)
    - Marcel Brunot, 1941-1942; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 45)
    - Letter from "Jean", 1950 October 22; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 46)
    - Official Letter Concerning Antoine Blanes, 1949 September 7; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 47)
    - Comité d'Action de la Résistance Bulletins, 1948 April 9; 1 folder (Box B-001233, Folder 48)
    - La Commission d'Histoire de l'Occupation et de la Libération de la France: Plan d'Enquête et de Questionnaire pour Les Mouvements de Résistance, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 1)
      Includes autograph note by Char: "ne pas repondre à ce questionnaire trop bien tourné!"
    - Letter from a Liaison Committee, 1951 March 4; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 2)
      Includes autograph note by Char: "même de bonne volonté, les crabes restent des crabes...", ("even of good will, the crabs remain crabs ...")
    - L'Assemblée Amicale d'Entraide des Anciens Officiers Correspondence and Convocations, 1946-1972; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 3)
      Includes the "First of the Resistance", the Democratic Party, received donations, etc.
    - "La Liberté passe en trombe", 1946 August 15; 1 box
      - "Cet anniversaire" Manuscript, 1946 August 15; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 4)
        Speech written by Char delivered to French broadcasting on August 15, 1946, with General de Lattre.
      - "La Liberté passe en trombe" Typescript, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 5)
        Annotated typescript of "Cet anniversaire," the title having been changed to "La Liberté passe en trombe."
    - Captain Alexandre Autograph Memo to the Durance-Altitude SAP Team, 1944 June 9; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 6)
  - Resistance II, 1942-1998; 3 boxes
    Consists of letters and some documents mostly addressed to Char from members of the Resistance network; a good number of materials are organized by geographic region in which members were stationed. Most date from after the war.
    - Compagnons de Céreste, 1942-1980; 2 boxes
      - List of Correspondents, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 7)
      - Albertingo, Emile, 1945-1974; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 8)
      - Armand, Emile, 1948 September 27; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 10)
      - Avon Roger, Henri et Clément, 1945-1952; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 9)
        15 letters.
      - Balazuc, Marc, 1946 May; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 10)
        Includes 2 letters regarding Balazuc receiving the Croix de guerre.
      - Bassanelly, Maurice, 1947-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 11)
      - Brunet, 1945 July- August; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 12)
        Includes 2 letters.
      - Cabot André, Gendarme et Sa Veuve, 1946-1980; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 13)
        Includes 4 letters.
      - Chaumien, Maurice, Alias "Armand", 1945-1971; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 17)
      - Charmasson, Arthur Christol, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 14)
        6 letters.
      - Charmasson, Bruno, 1948-1959; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 15)
        Includes letters and a letter of recommendation.
      - Chaudon, Roger, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 16)
      - Delfini, François, 1944-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 18)
        Folder contains an identification card with a photo of Delfini, as well as two notes.
      - Gillet, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 19)
      - Godchot, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 20)
      - Jeanjean, R., 1945-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 21)
        Includes a letter from André Jean Jean
      - Léon, Pierrot, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 22)
      - Julien, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 23)
      - Lignon, André, 1942-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 24)
      - Loretti, Marcel, 1943; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 25)
      - Nervi, Ferdinand, 1949 September 16; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 26)
      - Nestoux, Jean, 1946-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 27)
      - Briançon, Marcel et Arlette, 1945-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 28)
      - Recco, Vincent, 1945-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 29)
      - Ribiere, Roger, 1944-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 30)
      - Rieu, Jean (Gendarme), 1947-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 31)
      - Roux, Claude, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 32)
    - Compagnons de Forcalquier, 1944-1997; 2 boxes
      - List of Correspondents, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 33)
      - Bardouin, 1946-1956; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 34)
        Includes three photographs of the Bardouin family.
      - Cavagni, Robert (Son of Emile), 1945-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 35)
      - Cavagni, Pierre, 1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 36)
      - Derbez, Emile (Leo), 1946; 1 folder (Box B-001234, Folder 37)
      - Rostagne, Denis, 1947-1965; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 1)
      - Royer, Raymond, 1949-1961; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 2)
        Contains a note about [W.E.B.] DuBois.
      - Testanière, Marius, 1944-1997; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 3)
      - Testanière, Jean (Jeannot), 1948-1997; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 4)
      - Testanière, Ismael, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 5)
      - René Char Letters to Marius Testanière, 1949-1959; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 6)
      - Forcalquier, R. Vincent, 1957; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 7)
      - Dumay, Pougel, 1947; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 8)
      - Sicard, Tecla, 1954-1958; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 9)
    - Others, 1944-1998; 2 boxes
      - Beyne (Colonel), 1956 December 6; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 11)
      - Besson, Gabriel, 1944-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 12)
        Includes 6 letters and documents around his assassination and his last letter to Char.
      - Chaudon, Andree Delphine, 1945-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 13)
      - Christol, Albert, 1948-1955; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 13)
      - Domaine, E. Michaud, 1956; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 14)
      - Dubois, Sebastian and Launay, Michel to Maria Claude Char, 1998; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 15)
      - "Eva", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 16)
      - de Floquierol, Armand, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 17)
      - Fontaine, Joesph, 1945 February 12; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 18)
      - de Garnier, 1946 June; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 19)
      - Genin, A., 1951 March 16; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 20)
      - Gonnet, Maurice, 1946; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 21)
      - Martin, Jean, de Reillanne, 1948 November 8; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 12)
      - Maurice, Julien, 1945 August 21; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 22)
      - de Mazan, Jean Menut, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 23)
      - Pelloux, Lucien and Sabine, 1948 May 29; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 24)
      - Polyte, 1946 May 6; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 25)
      - Sidoine, Marcelle, 1946; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 14)
      - Sylvain, Blanc, 1954 October 16; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 26)
      - Thro, Henri, 1945 November 18; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 27)
      - Zyngerman, Pierre, Alias Léon St Germain, 1945-1987; 2 boxes
        Includes correspondence with Zyngerman and his family.
        - Zyngerman, Pierre, Alias Léon St Germain, 1945-1986; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 28)
        - Zyngerman, Pierre, Alias Léon St Germain, 1945-1986; 1 folder (Box B-001235, Folder 29)
        - Zyngerman, Pierre, Alias Léon St Germain, 1955-1987; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 1)
      - Unidentifed Correspondents, 1945-1948; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 2)
  - Resistance III, 1935-1987; 2 boxes
    Includes some classified and secret documents, including letters about assassinations, death sentences, and other related matters.
    - Concerning Alleged Communist Activities of Char and His Wife, 1940-1945; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 3)
      Includes notice of death sentences dated August 27-29, 1941.
    - Papelon, Louis, 1943; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 4)
      2 letters from Louis Papelon, assassinated in 1944.
    - Poulet Affair, 1943-1987; 1 box
      - Poulet Affair, 1943-1947; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 5)
      - Poulet Affair, 1948-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 6)
      - Poulet Affair, 1946-1987; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 7)
    - Potet, Jean, 1935-1940; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 8)
      Documents concerning Jean Potet, an informer. Includes 1 letter written by Char.
    - Bouvier, Emile, 1944-1957; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 9)
      Includes 1 autograph letter and 12 postcards from Char; 15 letters from Bouvier to Char; 2 attestations from Char; and 2 photographic portraits of Char dedicated to Emile Bouvier (probably at G. Braque in Varengeville).
    - Ribaille, Jean, 1945-1961; 1 box
      37 letters from Jean Ribaille relating to Emile Bouvier.
      - Ribaille, Jean, 1945-1956; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 10)
      - Ribaille, Jean, 1949-1961; 1 folder (Box B-001236, Folder 11)
    - Inderkummen, Pierre, 1945-1956; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 1)
      2 letters from Inderkummen, as well as letter from Jean Ribaille to Char concerning Inderkummen.
    - Louis Laurens Affair, 1946-1959; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 2)
      Includes documents, 7 letters from Emile Laurens, father of Louis, a statement by Char, and a typed summary of Char's statement with autograph notes.
    - SAP Correspondence, Reports, and Documents, 1943-1973; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 3)
      Includes 62 reports, actions memos and other documents; includes an autograph note by Char and 2 autograph orders to his companions.
  - Resistance IV, 1941-1968; 2 boxes
    Consists of various materials, including official letters and SAP records, such as attestation requests and personnel files, as well as documents relating to the Dubois case in which Char and his maquis countered accusations made by several local communist leaders under the direction of Georges Dubois in 1945.
    - Postwar Letters from French Ministries and Institutions, 1945-1968; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 4)
      11 letters from ministries, the History Committee of the Second World War, and other official letters.
    - Letters Requesting Attestations, 1944-1951; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 5)
    - René Char Military Booklet, Identification, and Attestation, 1944-1949; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 6)
    - SAP Personnel Files (Fiches Individuelles), 1943-1944; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 7)
      86 personal identification forms and one ID card (with photo)
    - Affaire Dubois, 1941-1964; 1 box
      - Louis Sidoine Correspondence, 1941-1943; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 8)
        Letters from and about prisoner of war Louis Sidoine, husband of Marcelle Sidoine, including several letters from Sidoine to his wife and daughter, Mireille, while imprisoned in Germany.
      - Letters of Denunciation, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 9)
        Copies.
      - Signed Note by Char, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 10)
      - Report Removing Dubois from SAP, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 11)
      - Documents Concerning Honors and Recognition, 1942-1964; 1 box
        - Various Official Documents, 1945-1964; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 12)
          Contains documents awarding Char for his service, a promotion letter, and an appointment as an honorary officer.
        - Citation à l'ordre des Armées, 1946; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 13)
        - Mission Order from Général Azan, with Attestation, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 14)
        - Genéral Cochet Attestation, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 15)
        - Camille Rayon, alias Archiduc, Attestation, 1942; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 16)
        - Acte d'Engagement Forces Françaises Combatants, 1943; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 17)
        - Forces Françaises Combatants Certificate, 1949; 1 folder (Box B-001237, Folder 18)
    - Radio Messages, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 1)
    - Photograph of René Char's Residence in Ceréste, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 2)
    - Alger, 1944-1945; 1 box
      - Captaine Richard Alexandre Identity Card, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 3)
      - René Char Identification Card, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 4)
      - Ordre de Mission, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 5)
      - Ordre de Mission Permanent, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 6)
      - Passe Temporaire, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 7)
      - Carte Verte Spéciale Opération, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 8)
      - Security Clearance Pass/Fingerprints of René Char (Richard Alexandre), 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 9)
        Copy.
      - Notes Concerning le Réseau Action, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 10)
      - Newsletters (Actions à Alger), 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 11)
        Includes 8 bulletins.
      - Song-poem by Compagnons d'Alger, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 12)
      - Photograph of Char in Uniform, 1944 August 24; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 13)
      - Car Loan Restitution for SAP Missions, 1945; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 14)
    - Letters Concerning the Resistance, 1943-1945; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 15)
      Over 40 letters to Commander Alexander, received airdrops, reports, lists of Forces Françaises Combatants (FFC) personnel and other documents surrounding Resistance activities of Char's network.
  - Resistance V, 1929 July 6-1976; 2 boxes
    Includes letters from various correspondents and a few documents. Colonel Péri, Général Azan, Commandant Pierre Michel, F. Delbert, and Roger Brielle are represented, among others. Many items date from the Liberation period.
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 1929 July 6-1962; 1 box
      - Unidentified Sender, 1929 July 6; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 16)
      - Miscellaneous Letters, 1940-1943; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 17)
        Includes letters from Robert Baudry, André Seigue, and others.
      - Miscellaneous Letters, 1944; 1 folder (Box B-001238, Folder 18)